lightthenight.org 2017-12-01

# PRIVACY POLICY | Leukemia and Lymphoma Society

_**PRIVACY POLICY OF THE LEUKEMIA & LYMPHOMA SOCIETY**_

The Leukemia & Lymphoma Society (LLS) has developed this privacy policy statement (“Privacy Policy”) to assist donors, visitors to and end users of our websites, mobile and social media platforms, as well as our online and offline donation platforms (collectively referred to as the “Sites”) in understanding the Personal Information we collect, how we use that Personal Information, how we share Personal Information with third parties, how we secure your Personal Information, how you can opt out of various communication channels we may use to contact you and how we make changes to our Privacy Policy.  “Personal Information,,” as we use the term in this Privacy Policy, means information that can identify a specific individual, such as a name, address, phone number or email address.  Please review this Privacy Policy before using or submitting Personal Information to the Sites.

__**The Personal Information We Collect**__

LLS collects information from users through several points on our Sites, such as making a donation through our direct mail program, at an event or online, ordering free materials, volunteering, signing up for discussion boards or shopping at the LLS Storefront. The types of data collectcollected by LLS will vary with your particular use of the Sites or your donation activity.  Some examples of the types of Personal Information LLS may collect through the Sites include:

**Contact Information**

LLS may ask you to provide certain contact information, such as, your name, phone number, address, or email address.

**Demographic & Survey Information**

LLS may collect demographic and general profile data (e.g., educational, professional, and geographic information). 

**Financial Information**

LLS may collect credit or debit card information.  Personal financial information in the form of a credit card number and expiration date are only collected if a user wishes to make an online donation through LLS online or make purchases at the LLS Storefront. This information is not stored or maintained by LLS when entered online. All online transactions are protected and securely transmitted using SSLthe most current encryption protocols/algorithms such as TLS/SSL.

**Transactional Information**

LLS may create and maintain a database of aggregated information (which will not identify any particular user) about the transactions that occur on the Sites (e.g., tool or feature (and related database) utilization, registration information, and activity, navigation, exit page tracking, or content selection data).

**Technical Information**

LLS may also collect Internet Protocol (IP) addresses or a unique identifier for a mobile device from users of LLS’ Sites as well as the date and time of access and the Web pages accessed.  LLS may also catalog your log-in information and the type of computer, browser, or operating system you use.

**Geolocation Data**

When you access and use the Sites, LLS may receive, store and process different types of information about your geographic location, including general information (e.g., zip code) and more specific information (e.g., GPS-based functionality on mobile devices used to access the Sites).  If you access the Sites through a mobile device and you do not want your device to provide LLS with location-tracking information, you can disable the GPS or other location-tracking functions on your device, provided that your device allows you to do so. Please see your device manufacturer’s instructions for further details.

__**How We Use Your Personal Information**__

The primary reason for LLS to collect Personal Information is to provide personalization options for users of our Sites, and to facilitate and enhance Site features that require user input, whether this information is submitted directly by the user of our Sites, or collected by use of technologies such as cookies, as discussed below.  Personal Information submitted through LLS Sites is only used for the purposes for which it was collected.  Below please find additional information on how LLS may use Personal Information collected from the Sites: 

**Contact Information**

LLS may use your contact information to provide you with information, materials and services, to enable you to make donations and to participate in activities, events, and offerings available through the Sites.  LLS may also use your contact information to (i) advertise its events, programs, products, and services, (ii) assist with security or fraud prevention or response measures, (iii) facilitate a website feature that requires user input, or(iv) to get in touch with you with respect to any transactions conducted through the Sites.

We also may share your contact information with third parties including our vendors, advertisers, or business partners, to (i) facilitate or implement any of our services, (ii) advertise the services or activities of others, (iii) advise you of LLS’ programs, events, volunteer opportunities, products or services, (iv) process payments, order fulfillment, or donations, or (v) allow for online registration for programs, events, or services. In addition, LLS may supplement the Personal Information collected from you with information about you obtained from other sources, such as LLS’s vendors, advertisers, or business partners,

Message boards and chat rooms may be available through the Sites. The forums will identify visitors as requested by the visitor. Please remember that any information you disclose in these areas becomes public information. Accordingly, you should always exercise caution when deciding to disclose personal information.

**Demographic & Survey Information**

LLS may use demographic information for marketing and management purposes in order to continue to provide or improve the Sites.  In addition, LLS may share aggregated survey results and aggregated demographic data (which will not identify any particular user) collected through the Sites with its vendors, business partners, the general public, the news media, and with the U.S. Government and state governments.

**Financial Information**

LLS will use financial information to facilitate a donation or other transaction, such as a purchase at the LLS Storefront.

**Transactional Information**

LLS may use transactional information for marketing and management purposes to provide or improve any products or services that LLS may offer.  In addition, LLS may also share such transactional data on an aggregated basis (which will not identify any particular user) with third parties, such as vendors, advertisers, or business partners. 

**Technical Information**

LLS may use technical information, such as your IP address or browser type, to helpdiagnose help diagnose problems with LLS’ servers, analyze Sites usage trends, track user movements on the Sites, and to otherwise improve, manage and monitor the Sites.

**Geolocation Data**

LLS may use geolocation data to personalize your Site experience on the Sites, e.g., to show local contacts and information relevant to your location.

**Business Transactions**

In the event that LLS goes through a business transaction such as a bankruptcy event, merger, investment transaction, or acquisition by another entity involving the sale of all or a portion of its assets, the Personal Information collected by LLS may be among the assets reviewed. 

**Legal Action**

LLS may disclose Personal Information when legally required to do so.  LLS may also disclose Personal Information to protect against misuse or unauthorized use of the Sites or to limit legal liability or to protect LLS’ interests or those of others.

__**Cookies**__

LLS or its vendors may use cookies, web beacons, tags, log-inlogin files or other similar data collection or tracking techniques to facilitate use of our Sites by our users, and to enrich your online experience with us.  A cookie is a piece of data stored on the user's computer tied to information about that user. LLS uses both session ID cookies and persistent cookies. For the session ID cookie, once users close the browser, the cookie is simply terminateserased. A persistent cookie is a small text file stored on the user's hard drive for an extended period of time. Persistent cookies can be removed by following Internet browser help file directions.

Persistent cookies are used to store the user's registration identification information from their basic registration and to facilitate their logging in to their personalized view of the Sites. Persistent cookies enable us to track and target the interests of our users to enhance their experience on our Sites.

Session cookies remember what chapter you are registered intoin or visiting online and who you are if you go from one LLS website to another in a session. This way we are able to cut down on the number of logins required when you visit various LLS websites during any given session.

Many consider the use of cookies and such identifiers to be an industry standard measure.  Consequently, your web browser is likely set to accept cookies or allow other identifiers.  If you would prefer not to receive cookies or allow identifiers, you can alter the configuration of your browser to refuse cookies or surf anonymously.  If you reject cookies, you may still use our websites, and all the informational resources provided through them. Your registration-based personalization options and the capacity of your browser to keep track of what chapter you are visiting online as you go from one of our sites to another, is lost if you reject cookies.

LLS uses a tracking utility provided by a third party vendor to track usage of specific web pages and other resources provided through our website. The vendor sets cookies as a method for compiling site usage information but these cookies are only used to compile demographic models of site usage and are not tied to the user's personal information.

__**Digital Advertising**__

LLS allows third parties to place cookies through our websitewebsites to collect information about your visit to our and other websites in order to offer you more relevant advertising across the Internet.  This practice is known as online behavioral advertising.  These cookies (placed by our third party vendors) contain no personally identifiable information, but they may contain demographic or interest-based information in de-identified form.  This information may also be linked to Personal Information (in hashed or encrypted form) that you have voluntarily submitted to LLS, such as your email address.  If you would like to opt out of the placement of these third party cookies, please visit www.aboutads.info/choices.  If you would like to opt out of third party use of your mobile device identifier for behavioral advertising, please see www.aboutads.info/appchoices.   Please note that if you delete, block, or otherwise restrict cookies, or if you use a different computer or Internet browser, you may need to renew your opt-out choice.  LLS does not host any form of advertising from our websites or email communications.

__**Third Party Intermediaries**__

LLS uses various third party transaction services to process online donations and provides the option of receiving certain of its online booklets, brochures, and fact sheets by mail through request forms on our websitesSites. These materials are shipped by the US Postal Service. Additional services for Light The Night Incentives,® incentives and ordering from the LLS Storefront also utilize third party vendors for ordering, fulfillment and customer service.

We will only provide these companies the information they need to deliver the service and prohibit them from using that information for any other purpose. These companies or organizations do not share or use Personal Information that may be obtained from these transactions for any secondary purposes.

LLS may need to share Personal Information with third parties in other limited circumstances. For example, we may release Personal Information to third parties to perform services on our behalf such as: advising you of our upcoming events, products, partnership offers, volunteer opportunities, and health-related information or processing credit card payments. LLS may also make your name and postal address available to other nonprofit organizations whose services or activities may be of interest to you. However, third parties retained by LLS to provide such services are obligated to maintain the confidentiality of this information and are not authorized to use this information for any purpose other than providing those services.

To the extent hyperlinks are utilized to access third party sites (not controlled, owned, or operated by LLS), you should be aware that these external or third party sites may collect Personal Information and are not subject to this Privacy Policy.  This Privacy Policy applies only to the Sites.  LLS suggests that you check the privacy policies of other web sites to determine how the proprietors of these third party sites will utilize your Personal Information.

__**Data Security**__

LLS maintains data security measures in line with current industry standards for the Sites to protect the Personal Information under its control against unauthorized access and disclosure.  These measures include the implementation of reasonableindustry recommended technical, physical and administrative data security safeguards.  More sensitive information, namely, your credit or debit card numbernumbers, are encrypted and protected with Payment Card Industry Data Security Standard (PCI DSS) guidelines employing the most current encryption software algorithms and protocols such as TLS/SSL when transmitted to LLS. online. LLS does not store or re-use credit card information is not stored or re-used.. Role based access ensures that only authorized personnel with specificunique IDs and passwords can access credit card transactions based on business needs, solely for the purpose of processing authorized transactions.  LLS does not have direct readable access to any credit card number but can view transactions through our credit card merchant gateway throughvia our processing provider in order to void, refund or adjust transactions.  LLS also requires that the vendors LLS engages with respect to the Sites employ reasonableindustry standard data security safeguards when carrying out their services on LLS’ behalf.  

__**Opt-Out**__

From time to time, LLS may also share donor names and mailing addresses with other reputable nonprofit organizations on a limited basis in exchange for limited access to the names and addresses of their constituents.  We have found this to be a cost effective method of reaching additional potential constituents.  These organizations will not have continued access to your name and address unless you choose to respond to their initial mailing.  We do not share email addresses or health related data in connection with this list exchange.

We respect our donors’ choices and control over their information.  You, as a donor may, at any time, have your name excluded from any donor list exchange activity.  We also recognize that you may wish to limit the ways in which we contact you, and we offer the following options for restricting internal and external sharing of your contact information:

Do not contact me by telephone.   
Do not contact me by postal mail.   
Do not contact me by email.   
Do not share my contact information with other nonprofit organizations.   
Limit your fund-raising appeals to semiannual solicitations only.   
Do not contact me.

To request that your name be excluded from list exchange activity or to otherwise change how LLS contacts you, please email us at [rmgdonorserviceslls@merkleinc.com](mailto:rmgdonorserviceslls@merkleinc.com) or feel free to contact us at [1-800-462-7831](tel:+1-800-462-7831).

If you opt back into a specific service, you will receive communication in that manner regardless of your overall opt out selections.  For example, if you request a newsletter subscription, we will provide you that subscription, even if you previously asked us not to contact you at all.  We will take all reasonable efforts to ensure that your requests are honored in a timely fashion.  Please note that if you are an active participant in one of our fundraising events, such as Team In Training® or Light The Night Walk®, you may receive communications related to that event regardless of your overall opt out selections.  If you do not wish to receive emails about that event, please opt out using the “unsubscribe” link provided in the communication.

Email: [rmgdonorserviceslls@merkleinc.com](mailto:rmgdonorserviceslls@merkleinc.com)

Postal Mail:

The Leukemia & Lymphoma Society   
PO Box 98018   
Washington, DC 20090-8018

__**California Residents**__

Companies that collect Personal Information from California residents and disclose such information to third parties (including affiliated entities) for marketing purposes must, in response to a request by a consumer, either (1) provide a list detailing the categories of information shared and the entities to which such information was provided, or (2) provide a mechanism by which a consumer may opt-out of having his or her information shared with third parties.  LLS has elected the second option, and you may request that your Personal Information not be shared with third parties by utilizing the opt-out right or sending your request, including your full name, email address and postal address, to Attn. Privacy, Chief Marketing Officer, The Leukemia & Lymphoma Society, 3 International Drive, Suite 200, Rye Brook, NY 10573.  California residents are also entitled to know that they may file grievances and complaints with California Department of Consumer Affairs, 400 R Street, Suite 1080, Sacramento, CA 95814; or by phone at 916-445-1254 or 800-952-5210; or by email to dca@dca.ca.gov.

__**Our Commitment to Children's Privacy**__

Protecting the privacy of the very young is especially important. For that reason, we never collect or maintain information on our website from those we actually know are under the age of 13.

The Children's Online Privacy Protection Act (COPPA) protects the Personal Information of children under the age of 13. This applies to individually identifiable Personal Information about a child that is collected online, such as full name, home address, email address, telephone number or any other information that would allow someone to identify or contact the child. The Act and the COPPA Rule also cover other types of information--for example, hobbies, interests and information collected through cookies or other types of tracking mechanisms--when they are tied to individually identifiable information. It is important for you to understand this law; we encourage you to read more about COPPA.

__**Note to Parents on Our Privacy Policy**__

LLS is committed to providing a safe, secure, and fun online experience for children who visit our Sites. We are dedicated to safeguarding any Personal Information collected online and to helping parents and children have positive experiences on the Internet. Consistent with the Children's Online Privacy Protection Act of 1998, we will never knowingly request personally identifiable information from anyone under the age of 13 without prior verifiable parental consent. A parent or guardian may revoke their consent and ask that information about their child be deleted from the site by contacting our offices via mail (see: address below) or email supportservices@lls.org. To do this or to review Personal Information collected from children, we must verify the identity of the requesting parent. When a parent or guardian revokes consent, we will stop collecting, using, or disclosing information from that child. To respect the privacy of parents, information collected and used for the sole purpose of obtaining verifiable parental consent or providing notice is not maintained in retrievable form by the site if parental consent is not obtained after a reasonable time.

__**Notification of Changes**__

If LLS changes its Privacy Policy, changes to this privacy statement will be posted, with prominent links to the new policy positioned on the LLS homepage, and other places we deem appropriate, so our users are always aware of what information we collect, how we use it, and under what circumstances, if any, we disclose it. LLS will use information in accordance with the Privacy Policy under which the information was collected.

__**Governing Law**__

This Privacy Policy shall be governed by and construed in accordance with the laws of the state of New York.  If you are located outside of the United States when you use the Sites, any information you submit thereto will be transferred to the United States.  Accordingly, by using the Sites and submitting Personal Information theretothere, you authorize the transfer of your Personal Information to the United States.  If any part of this Privacy Policy is determined to be invalid or unenforceable pursuant to applicable law, then the invalid or unenforceable provision or part will be deemed suspended and a valid, enforceable provision that most closely matches the intent of the original provision or part and the remainder of this Privacy Policy shall continue in full force and effect.

__**Contacting Us**__

LLS reserves the right to change this policy at any time. Since any changes will be posted on this page, we encourage you to check this page regularly. Your continued use of the Sites will constitute your acceptance of such changes. If you have any further questions regarding this privacy policy or the use of your Personal Information under this Privacy Policy, you can contact us by email at supportservices@lls.org or by postal mail at:

Deborah J. Matz, Esq.

SVP, Legal & Enterprise Risk Management

The Leukemia & Lymphoma Society

3 International Drive, Suite 200

Rye Brook, NY 10573

Additional Information

This Privacy Policy is personal between you and us, and no one else shall be deemed a third party beneficiary of this policy.

This Privacy Policy was last updated on August 2, 2016.

USE OF THIS SITE SIGNIFIES YOUR AGREEMENT TO THE TERMS OF USE AND THIS PRIVACY POLICY.
